Okay, so in the previous lesson, we have
been
learning about fluid statics.
And today, we are going to be learning
about
fluid dynamics, just a quick overview, and
the
introduction to a new formula, Bernoulli's
equation.
And this formula basically governs all of
what
you need for Bernoulli's equation.
So, what is Bernoulli's equation?
I'll just start off the lesson by
introducing
this. It is
p plus one over two rho v
squared plus rho gh equals constant.
Or, yeah. So basically, p is the static
pressure,
and this is just like the pressure of the
molecular
motion inside the fluid. I'll just go over
what
each of these mean really quickly. You
don't
really have to know them. This is one over
two
density v squared is dynamic pressure,
which
is due to the fluid's motion.
And basically, it states that if you have
a
faster flowing liquid, the faster this
pressure
will be. So this is static.
This is dynamic, or flowing.
And this is a hydrostatic pressure.
And basically, if you recognize this, it's
somewhat
like the gravitational potential energy.
So basically, it's pressure dependent on
height.
And this also, basically, the higher the
fluid
is, the greater this term.
And since this is equal to a constant, we
can
modify this equation, actually, to make it
very,
very useful for our calculations.
p one plus one over two rho v
squared plus rho gh.
The initial, just add one to everything,
equals
p two plus one over two rho two v two
squared
plus rho two gh two.
And you might be wondering, wow, this is
such
a big equation. This is gonna probably be
very
complicated. But not really. In most
questions,
a lot of these stay the same.
For example, usually sometimes the height
will
stay the same. So these will cancel out.
And usually the liquid stays the same as
well.
So a lot of these will not matter. And you
will
only need parts of these for parts of your
question.
But this is a good formula to know, or to
know
how to use. And now we are going
to use another example.
Let's say we have water flowing through,
let's
say, a pipe. So I'm going to draw a pipe
over
here. And all of a sudden, this water now
starts flowing through a smaller pipe.
And you need to calculate the change in
velocity
of the pipe.
So let's fill this with water.
First of all, we know, what do we know?
Well, we know that the fluid density is
the
same everywhere. It's 1,000 kilograms per
metre
squared, like I've said before, sorry,
metres
cubed. And let's say our pipe diameter is
0.1 metres.
And this is half, so we would be 0.05
metres.
And let's say the water is moving, oops,
the
water is moving at a speed of 2 metres per
second,
right? And the pressure in this
section is 100,000, sure.
And let's say you don't want to find the
velocity.
Let's say you want to find the new
pressure
in the narrow section, because if you use
common
sense, it's going to move faster. So let's
find
the pressure, P2.
Well, first of all, we need to find the
velocity
in the narrow section first.
And we can use something called the
continuity
equation. And that basically states that
the
area times the velocity is constant.
So sorry, this is also another formula you
need
to know. And so the first area is
0.05 r squared times pi.
So pi times r1 squared times
v1, which is, I'll just write v1 for now,
equals,
well, this is pi times r2 squared times
v2.
So what is r1? Well, r1 is 0.05 squared
times
v1 is 2 metres per second. Again, I'll
just
not use units for simplicity's sake.
r2 is 0.025 squared times
v2. And if you plug in all your numbers,
you
should get about pi times 0.05 squared
times 2 divided by pi, so pi is cancelled
out,
0.025 squared, you should get exactly 8
metres
per second. And this will be the speed
it's
flowing through here. So notice that it's
exponential.
If the diameter decreases by a half, the
velocity
increases by four times.
So it's exponential. Now we have the new
velocity.
So we're going to use our Bernoulli's
equation
over here. I'm just going to real quick
copy
and paste it. Okay.
Now we have the new Bernoulli's equation.
We could just, oops, lag.
We can use it. So if you plug everything
into
the equation, we have, um, this stays
constant because in this case, the height
of
the fluid is always the same.
So this stays constant. So our simplified
equation
will be p1 plus one over two rho one times
v1
squared equals p2 plus one over two rho
two
v2 squared. And now p1 is, as
we know, 100,000 plus one over two, the
density
of the fluid. We know it's just a density
of
water, which is 1000 times v1 is two
squared
is equal to p2, which we want to solve
plus
one over two times 1000, because it's
still
the same liquid doesn't change. And v2 is
as
we calculated eight squared.
And when you plug this in your calculator,
you
will get a
one sec, you'll
get 70,000 pascals. So
notice that 70,000 is less than the
initial
pressure and the higher container. So you
might
think that since it's being squeezed into
such
a tight spot, the pressure is not going to
be
as great. But it's actually the opposite.
If you go inside, even though the velocity
is
going to increase, the pressure actually
decrease.
And in conclusion, basically, this is the
formula
that governs all fluid mechanics.
Thank you for watching.